Guide to the Robert L. Benney Research Collection 1933-1978, undated (bulk, 1942-1944) PR 250
New-York Historical Society
Robert L. Benney research collection
1933-1978, undated (bulk, 1942-1944)
New-York Historical Society
Benney, Robert L., 1904-
PR 250
4.85 Linear feet (5 boxes)
Robert Benney, a successful commercial artist and illustrator gained recognition as a war artist-correspondent during World War II.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert L. Benney, 1978.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in five series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Personal Papers
Series III. Printed Matter
Series IV. Photographs
Series V. Scrapbooks
Biographical Note
Robert Benney, painter and illustrator, was born in 1904 in Romania. (It appears that he often listed his place of birth as New York City, but his vaccination record, found in this collection, as well as his obituary, printed in the New York Times, list his birthplace as Romania.) He was raised in New York City, and studied art at Cooper Union from 1921 to 1925 and the National Academy of Art from 1928 to 1932. At the age of nineteen, while still in art school, Benney opened his own studio creating illustrations for New York newspapers and magazines. In the late 1930s, he received commissions from several Hollywood studios, working to document theater productions and stage personalities.
Although a successful commercial illustrator and painter, Benney is most well known for his work as a war artist-correspondent during World War II. In 1943 he was hired by Abbott Laboratories to document the Naval Aviation Department's activities in the Pacific. He was commissioned again by Abbott in 1944 to illustrate the Army Medical Department in the South Pacific, where he covered the invasion of Saipan.
After WWII, Benney continued to work as an artist-correspondent. He traveled to North Africa in 1954 to illustrate the activities of the United States Air Force. Then in 1968, Benney again offered his skills as an artist, serving with the Marines and covering their activities in Vietnam.
Between his travels with the military, Benney taught art at Pratt Institute from 1949 to 1952 and at the Dutchess County College from 1964 to 1973. He also continued working as a commercial artist. He was commissioned by large corporations such as the American Sugar Refining Company, Standard Oil Company and Western Electric.
Robert Benney passed away in Boston in June 2001. His work can be found in the permanent collections of many important institutions including the Corcoran Gallery of Art and the Smithsonian Institute, both in Washington, D.C., the Dallas Museum of Fine Arts in Dallas, TX and The Society of Illustrators in New York City, NY as well as in all branches of the Armed Services.
Scope and Contents
The Robert L. Benney Research Collection spans the period from 1940-1978 and includes correspondence to and from Benney, personal papers and records, reproductions of artwork, ephemera, newspaper and magazine clippings and scrapbooks.
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Offset lithography.; Photographic prints.; New York (N.Y.); Saipan (Northern Mariana Islands); Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York.; Saipan, Battle of, Northern Mariana Islands, 1944.; War artists -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, American; Benney, Robert L., 1904-; Colby, Elliot
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Correspondence contains letters dating from 1942-1975 and includes personal, professional and official military correspondence. The letters have been divided into two subseries, Personal and Official, and arranged by date.
  Subseries I. Personal includes both personal and professional correspondence. Professional letters include those from The American Sugar Refining Company, Abbott Laboratories, Associated American Artists, New York Times, and Twentieth Century Fox Film Corporation. Personal letters include correspondence from soldiers and officials he met abroad including Elliot Colby, M.D., Richard Holtz, M.D., and Lt. William Hewitt.
  Subseries II. Official consists of letters from military sources regarding his trips to the Pacific during World War II. Included are letters containing Benney's orders, transportation instructions and permits for departure as well as letters to military officials regarding his credentials. Also found are memos of instruction including Field Sanitation, Medical and sanitary data on Micronesia, and What to do if a Man is Shot During Combat. Located at the end of this subseries are a group of envelops without attached correspondence, one of which has a small sketch on its reverse.
  - Subseries I: Personal
    - From Benney, 1942-1969, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Benney, 1942-1949 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - To Benney, 1951-1975 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - To Benney, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - To Mrs. Benney, 1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II. Official
    - To Benney - Orders, 1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - To Others - re. Benney's Credentials, 1942, 1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Misc. Memos, 1943-1944, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Envelopes - Empty, 1942-1945, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Personal Papers
  Series II. Personal Papers contains biographical information, lists and inventories of artwork, handwritten notes, and ephemera. Of note are two diaries: Benney's datebook from 1944, mainly recording addresses, lists and travel expenses and a diary of military doctor Col. Elliot Colby, dated May 28 through November 5, [1944], recording events in Saipan. Other material includes Benney's vaccination record, his blood donor card, invitations and an Overseas Edition for Armed Forces of The New Yorker, from July 22, 1944.
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-1954, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Artwork - Locations, Inventories, Notes, 1947, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Biographical Information, 1953-1977, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Elliot Colby Diary, [1944] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ephemera, 1942-1944, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Interview with Benney - Transcription, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notes, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Teaching Material, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III: Printed Matter
  Series III. Printed Matter is comprised of a variety of publicity and includes printed examples of Benney's work. Newspaper and magazine articles illustrated by Benney as well as articles about Benney and his work can be found in this series. Publications include Pageant, Argosy, The American Legion, Our Navy and The Saturday Evening Post. Also included are exhibition announcements and catalogs from shows that featured his work.
  Much of this material is oversized and has been separated. Included are several reproductions of his sketches, some of which are signed. One flat file folder contains several halftone prints of various paintings and illustrations, including an image of the Domino Sugar Factory in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, drawn for the American Sugar Refining Company.
  - Miscellaneous (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Exhibit Announcements, Catalogs, Guides, 1940-1978, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19-21)
    General note
    See also: Oversize Material
  - Illustration - Annual Reports, 1953-1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Illustration - Magazines, 1950-1960, 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Magazine Articles - Full Magazines & Clippings, 1943-1960, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1933, 1940-1972, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
- Series IV: Photographs
  Series IV. Photographs includes images of Benney taken primarily during his travels in Saipan, Cuba, Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands. Many of these photographs were taken while he was working as a war artist-correspondent in the Pacific during World War II and show Benney, in uniform, drawing soldiers in hospitals and in the field. Another series of portraits show Benney in Cuba while on assignment for The American Sugar Refining Company, posed with sugarcane cutters.
  - Military, 1944, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cuba, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous, 1945, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
- Series V: Scrapbooks
  Series V. Scrapbooks contain loose pages with attached newspaper and magazine clippings, letters, photographs, book covers and other examples of Benney's work. Scrapbooks are sorted by content, and are annotated with handwritten notes, which Benney added to describe various items. One group of pages contains letters from military offices and business contacts, most regarding commissioned artwork. Scrapbook pages labeled "Illustration" contain clippings of magazine work, covers of novels and other examples of commercial work. "Printed Matter" pages include some of the same type of clippings, but also include ephemera, invitations, photographs and other pieces not related to commercial illustration. Many of these pages are brittle and must be handled with care. There are photographic reproductions of some of these scrapbook pages, filed at the end of the series.
  - Art Reproductions (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Correspondence (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Illustration (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33-35)
  - Illustration, cont. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36-38)
  - Printed Matter (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39-41)
  - Clippings - reproduced pages (Offsite-box 4, Folder 42)
- From Series III: Printed Matter
  - Oversize Material, Boxed
    - Artwork - Reproductions of sketches (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
    - Exhibit Catalogs (Offsite-box 5, Folder 44)
    - Illustration - Magazines (Offsite-box 5, Folder 45)
    - Illustration - Matted Clippings (Offsite-box 5, Folder 46-47)
    - Magazine Articles - Full magazines (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
    - Magazine Articles - Clippings (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
  - Oversize Material, Flat File
    - Oversize Prints (Folder OS-1)